A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, International Urbanization Survey Records FA1543
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, International Urbanization Survey Records
1970-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1543
2.1 Cubic Feet 5 boxes (4 legal document containers and 1 half legal document container)
Biographical / Historical
In 1970, the Ford Foundation initiated an International Urbanization Survey designed to review and assess the effects of urbanization in the developing world. The Survey staff travelled to countries where the Foundation maintained field offices to observe urbanization issues for themselves. In addition, the Survey drew upon the experiences of Foundation personnel assigned to field offices in developing countries. The Survey was based in Athens, Greece and conducted by John P. Robin, Colin Rosser, and Frederick C. Terzo. The Survey covered select countries in Asia, Africa, and Latin America and consisted of three basic questions:
1. How are the developing countries themselves responding to rapid urbanization and its consequences?
2. What are international aid agencies doing to advise and assist them?
3. What would be the most useful and effective contribution of the Ford Foundation's international program in the field?
At the conclusion of the Survey, Foundation staff's field notes on phases of urbanization in specific countries were expanded into working papers (see related materials). Additional working papers were provided by Foundation personnel with a depth of field knowledge, and by consultants' expertise either in specific countries or in topics of special interest. The working papers resulting from the International Urbanization Study were originally created by Ford Foundation staff to guide the Foundation in making informed judgments on future programs related to urban conditions in developing countries, but they were ultimately shared widely in the development field. The work of the Survey was completed with the publishing of a final report in 1972.
Related Materials
Working papers associated with the International Urbanization Survey can be found in Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 1-3254
Urbanization in Colombia (Reports 002008-001), 1972
Urbanization in Colombia (Reports 002008-002), 1972
Urbanization in Brazil (Reports 002009), 1972
Urbanization in Jamaica (Reports 002010), 1972
Urbanization in Peru (Reports 002011), 1972
Urbanization in Venezuela (Reports 002012), 1972
Urbanization in Chile (Reports 002013), 1972
Urbanization in Tropical Africa: A demographic introduction (Reports 002014), 1972
Urbanization in Nigeria: A planning commentary (Reports 002015), 1972
Urbanization in Zambia (Reports 002016), 1972
Urbanization trends and prospects (Reports 002017), 1972
Urbanization and government policy in Morocco (Reports 002018), 1972
Urbanization in Turkey (Reports 002019), 1972
Urbanization in India (Reports 002020), 1972
Urbanization in Thailand 1973? (Reports 002021), 1972-1973
Urbanization in the developing countries: the response of international assistance (Reports 002022), 1972
Infrastructure problems of the cities of developing countries (Reports 002023), 1972
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into one series:
Series 1: Correspondence and Research Materials
The purpose of the numbering system present in the collection could not be determined at the time of processing. The original order of the material was maintained.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary. This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as part of Program Strategy records, Accession 2019:012.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily contains correspondence related to the logistics and findings of the Ford Foundation's International Urbanization Survey. The Survey was conducted between 1970-1972 to review and assess the effects of urbanization in the developing world. The Foundation used their findings to plan international programming related to urbanization and publish working papers based on their observations.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Developing Countries; Ford Foundation; International affairs; Urbanization; Urbanization -- Africa; Urbanization -- Latin America; Urbanization -- Asia -- Congresses.
- Correspondence and Research Materials, 1970-1973; 1
  - John P. Robin - Urbanization Project and Related Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - John P. Robin - Delhi Conference, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ford Foundation Chron, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - 100 - Project Budget - Logistic Procedures, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 102 - International Urbanization Survey Plan of Operation - Pre-history, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 105 - Administrative Correspondence with New York, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - 105a - Administrative Correspondence with New York - Press Releases, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 105a - Administrative Correspondence with New York - Grant Actions, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 108 - Administrative Correspondence with Athens Center of Ekistics, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 201 - Travel Programs and Arrangements, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 202 - Ford Foundation - Asia, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    Sections include: India, Indonesia
  - 203 - Ford Foundation - New York - Middle East and Africa Division, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Ghana, Kenya, Nigeria, Tanzania, Zambia, Lebanon
  - 204 - Ford Foundation - New York - Latin America Division, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Argentina, Chile, Mexico, Peru, Puerto Rico
  - 205 - Lou Winnick, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 206 - Leslie Green, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 207 - Comments on Terms of Reference, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 208 - Pendleton Western Europe Survey, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - 209 - C. P. Andrade, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 210 - Consultants - General, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 211 - Oscar Gish, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 212 - Otto Koeningsberger, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - 213 - Research Assistants, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 215 - Jaime Valenzuela, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 216 - Beverley Berstein, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 217a - Survey Reports (General - Latin America - Special Studies), 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
    Sections include: Colombia, Mexico, Peru, Venezuela, O.H. Koenigsberger, Hugh Tinker, General, Latin America, Argentina, Brazil, Chile
  - 217b - Survey Reports (Africa - Asia), 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
    Sections include: Africa, Ghana, Kenya, Asia, India, Malaysia, Turkey
  - 217c - Comments on the International Agencies Report, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 218 - Professor Rusen Keles, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 219 - Katherine Marshall Johnson, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - 402 - African Urbanization - General, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - 407 - Kenya, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - 408 - Nigeria, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - 409 - Zambia, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - 410 - Algiers, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - 411 - Mexico, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - 500 - Latin America - Colombia, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - 700 - Far East - General, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - 800 - Urban Infrastructure Survey, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - 801 - USAID, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - 802 - Organization of American States, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - 803 - World Bank, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - 803a - Inter-American Development Bank, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - 804 - Department of Housing and Urban Development (USA), 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - 805 - United Nations - New York, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - 806 - United Nations - General, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - 807 - World Health Organization, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - 808 - International Labour Office, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - 809 - Ministry of Overseas Development (England), 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - 810 - International Research and Training Centers, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    Architectural Association, England
    Centre for Environmental Studies, England
    Centre d'Etudes de Geographic Tropical, Talence, France
    Organisation de Cooperation et de Developpement Economiques (OCDE), France
    Secretariat des Missions d'urbanisme et d'Habitat, France (SMUH)
    Institute of Race Relations, England
    ACCION, New York
    Department of State
    American Institute of Architects, Washington, DC
    Institute of Public Administration, New York
    Planning and Development Collaborative International (PADCO), New York
    I. M. Pei and Partners, New York
    Special Program for Urban and Regional Studies of Developing Areas (SPURS), Mass.
    Canadian centers
  - 811 - Regional Research and Training Centers, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    Congo
    Ghana
    India
    Kenya
    Israel
    Nigeria
    Pakistan
    Senegal
    Singapore
    Tanzania
    Thailand
    Zambia
  - 812 - Universities, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    USA, Latin America, Africa
  - 812a - University of Birmingham (Prof. Maddick), 1971 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - 813 - International Workshops, Seminars, Conferences, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - 814 - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (USA), 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - 815 - Resources for the Future, Inc., Washington, D.C., 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - 816 - Colin Buchanan and Partners, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - 817 - Meetings with International Agencies - Minutes, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - 818 - Inter-agency Group in Urban Development, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - 819 - Smithsonian Institution, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Staff Biographies, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Terms of Reference, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Summary Statement, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Checklists, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Athens Office Preparations, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 71)